Inheritance enables a class to reuse code from another class
In this example
We have the class Apple
That inherits from Fruit
Specified by the extends keyword
Fruit
Then becomes the superclass of Apple
Which in turn becomes a subclass of Fruit
In addition to its own members, Apple now gains all accessible members in Fruit
Except for its constructors
The other members seen here
All comes from the
Root class object
A class in java
May only inherit from 1 superclass
And if you don't specify one,
It will implicitly inherit from objects
Conceptually
A subclass
Is a specialization of a superclass
This means that Apple here
Is a kind of Fruit
As well as an Object
And can therefore be used anywhere a Fruit or an Object is expected
For example,
If we create an instance of an Apple
We can upcast it to a Fruit
Since a subclass contains everything in the superclass
The Apple is
Now seen as a Fruit
So we can only access the Fruit's members
When we then downcast the class back into an Apple
The fields specific to Apple remains unchanged
Beacuse the Fruit only encapsulated the Apple
It did not convert it
The downcast has to be made explicit
Since downcasting an actual Fruit into an Apple is not allowed
We can test to see if an object can be cast to a class
Using the instanceof operator
This operator
Returns true
If the left side object can be cast into the right side type without causing an exception
.